<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Bit Lucid Oval Gem]]></title>
  <link href="http://cuiyingchao.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cuiyingchao.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-03T16:16:45+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://cuiyingchao.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Richard]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[野火烧不尽——国人的英雄情结]]></title>
    <link href="http://cuiyingchao.github.io/blog/2013/11/03/yehuo1/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-03T14:55:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://cuiyingchao.github.io/blog/2013/11/03/yehuo1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>最近开始看龙应台的《野火集》。这本书收录了作者在上世纪八十年代发表的一系列针砭时弊的文章，直言台湾社会的种种病症，引起了很大反响。其中的文章短小精悍，茶余饭后翻看一篇，活动活动人文思维，也算是一种休息。</p>

<p>第一篇文章就很有趣，标题为“中国人，你为什么不生气”，其中讲到“闻恶不惊、见丑不怒”的中国人，麻木地生存在当时台湾病态的社会中。虽然已经过去近三十年，其中的道理和部分现象却恰好与时下大陆社会百态吻合。旧方可医新疾。</p>

<p>野火集不但收录龙应台本人的文章，也收录回应作者的一些佳作。在“中国人，你为什么不生气”这篇文章后面，就附有罗肇锦所作的一篇“中国人当然不生气”。作为回应，罗先生从家庭教育入手，剖析中国传统社会的潜规则，耐心解释了传统文化对国人不愿“扬善惩恶”的心理所起到的潜移默化的影响、塑造。</p>

<p>看龙先生的文章没有太多感觉，当下愤青太多，各方面的批评也不少，实在是够了。倒是罗先生的文章有些意思，也许在分析了中国人为什么不生气之后，能对问题有建设性的改良方案。</p>

<p>罗先生在文章中说，中国人自小就受“家”本位文化的影响，干什么事儿都先想想是不是对自己一家子有利。古人给出的职业规划也说“修身齐家治国平天下”，我的理解，“修身”也是为了“齐家”。对于大多数人，“齐家”已经是人生赢家了，毕竟“治国平天下”的鸿愿只有少数精英才能做到。中国政治可以由精英领导，打出以人为本的旗号，中国文化却只能跟随大众品味，以家为本。</p>

<p>明白了家本位的传统，自然就明白了为什么更多的人选择“舍大家顾小家”、“损人利己”，屡屡挑战以集体利益为核心的道德准则。在西方，有人为大众代言，争取到了共同的利益，他就是英雄，受人尊崇、争相模仿的英雄。而在东方，这样的人也会受人尊崇，写入文化，贴上中华文明优秀代表的标签，却很少有人愿意去模仿。只崇拜，不模仿，令西方诧异的东方哲学。</p>

<p>从这个角度出发，斗胆揣测一下中西民主的形式。在西方，政治家考虑尽可能释放大众的英雄主义情怀，努力给民众提供各种成为英雄的机会，当越来越多英雄涌现的时候，社会发展就会大踏步前进。所以对西方政客来说，民主是社会的基石。但中国的情况却不一样，中国人不愿意成为英雄，更擅长经营家族利益。所以这时候就需要有强大的中央权威去规范调节各家的利益，维持稳定的局面，让更多的人能把精力用到“齐家”上，而不必担心战乱、纷争、动荡。所以纵观中国历史，善于调和家族矛盾的政权统治中国的时期，往往是国家强盛、社会进步的时期，同时也不可避免的是权力高度集中的时期。所以从中国的角度来说，民主更多的内容是如何调节好家族利益，如何通过改善利益分配制度刺激全部家庭的成长和进步，而不是大放权。</p>

<p>中国历史上从未有中央政权主动放弃权力，除了中华民国临时政府。如果中央政府权威不再，比个人民主更有可能发生的结局是地方割据，是动荡和纷争，是中国家庭最不希望看到的局面。</p>

<p>附上野火集两篇文章原文：
<a href="http://www.oklink.net/a/0008/0828/yhj/001.htm">http://www.oklink.net/a/0008/0828/yhj/001.htm</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Survive From Insecurity]]></title>
    <link href="http://cuiyingchao.github.io/blog/2013/09/22/survive-from-insecurity/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-22T13:10:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://cuiyingchao.github.io/blog/2013/09/22/survive-from-insecurity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I used to suffer from insecurity for 2 half years, deeply into disturbing the normal life. I know the fact that many conditions during one&rsquo;s life lead to feeling unsafe and mostly fade away in a very short period of time.
But what came to me was that, I felt strong uneasy lasting 5 to 6 months each time for twice. During the 1st half year I went into this illness, I thought a lot of things, reflecting myself, observing different people in neighbor, finding answers in books, watching movies as well as doing sports to refit myself.</p>

<p>None was helpful enough to get me out of the depression.</p>

<p>After the professional intervention and healthy training, I was reborn from the 1st half year depression life. I became so happy and so curious about every thing around me. My life went into a very open way and I wanted to try every thing attractive to me, which seemed meaningless in my earlier depression time. So I started to change my view to a statistical way, which means that the probability of getting good things in life is an uniformly distributed fact. The more chance we try, the higher probability we get it. And following this way, I made a &ldquo;wonderful&rdquo; time schedule to optimize my time consuming both for living and working.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, the method I was relying on was proved wrong soon in less than one year&rsquo;s time after I fell into depression again. During the 2nd lasting unhappy period, I tried to avoid modeling the world to make my heart comfortable, but thought directly into the very simple question: <strong>Why would I fall into depression?</strong> Obviously I didn&rsquo;t manage to settle it in the gap of the 1st depression period and the 2nd. And bad things happened again to take my soul into the evil world.</p>

<p>I came out of the 2nd period of depression with the help of great support of my family &amp; my girlfriend, as well as keeping healthy training myself. This time, I felt becoming positive gradually, not jumping directly into happiness as the 1st time, and I made more mental adjustment to figure out what on earth made me depressed.<strong>The final answer comes into insecurity.</strong></p>

<p>From what I see as I grew up, young people who are extremely excellent in their school work are more likely to feel kind of insecurity. I don&rsquo;t know why but I will list it as an assumption. Maybe they are more sensitive to grade, comparison and the judges from others, since a bit of insecurity will alert one to achieve more little by little.</p>

<p>As the challenging varies from time to time, it is very hard to balance the property mood of insecurity beneficial to success. Especially for perfectionists, they will feel more and more insecurity when handling tough tasks in the way of pursuing the best solution. And when the trial and error scheme crash, they themselves break down too by a sense of every trial is meaningless.</p>

<p>The feeling of insecurity makes one focus on inner world more than the outer world, thus believing himself rather than getting help from others. What&rsquo;s more, one will have the fully control of his inner world and manage it in a optimal way, which is deterministic and highly scheduled. But to our disappointment, the outer world is of highly uncertainty, one cannot optimize the inner world plan to get the best solution for granted. This does really hurt. To avoid facing this natural rule directly, one may trust the tricks in <strong>success theories</strong>, such as try more time, do the rehearsal once again to gain a high probability of achieving it. But the simple fact is, uncertainty is uncertainty! No one controls whether it happens by probabilities. <strong>Being an adult needs to accept the uncertainty of the world and game with it rather than do more sampling to avoid the insecurity.</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Where do I want to live]]></title>
    <link href="http://cuiyingchao.github.io/blog/2013/09/17/where-do-i-want-to-live/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T19:18:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://cuiyingchao.github.io/blog/2013/09/17/where-do-i-want-to-live</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Welcome to my blog.</strong></p>

<p>This blog is used to document my daily intuitions and inductions, mainly focused in the area of science and life philosophy. As the blog name shows, I want the following documents could be helpful to see the iceberg beneath the sea, step by step.</p>

<p>I like to collect cool projects/tools to improvement visual enjoyment and human-nature interaction. As time goes, I will put the most interesting ones onto this platform. Hopefully you will enjoy it.</p>

<p>The blog is under construction, welcome to any suggestions.</p>

<h6>Regards</h6>

<h6>Richard</h6>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
